hello and welcome
it's March 9th 2023 we're an active
guest stream number 38.1 here with Max
Berg
thank you Max for joining this is going
to be great really looking forward to
your presentation and discussion so
appreciation again for joining and
looking forward to what you'll share
with us today
yeah thank you Daniel for having me
um
as I was introduced my name is Max back
I come from the University of Marburg
and I'm a clinical psychologist I want
to do a little bit of impression
management first so Marburg is next to
Frankfurt in case you don't know it's a
small or medium city in in Germany and
regarding me I'm interested in the
intersection of Clinical Psychology
neuroscience and philosophy that doesn't
mean that I'm an expert in all of these
fields of course I'm
I have a lot of knowledge in Clinical
Psychology I would say and the rest is
more of my hobbies and so it's important
that you keep in mind to expect a
clinical perspective today I'm not an
expert on like uh Bayesian mathematics
or anything like that I know a little
bit about it and I've read uh books
about it and try to keep myself updated
but it's not my expertise my expertise
is Clinical Psychology
and one I want to present today is like
a paper about depressive rumination but
we will see that it's not important that
it's depressive rumination and
rumination is a much broader construct
here and
um we want to
[Music]
re-rephrase like the Press of rumination
from an active inference perspective and
this is one of what we want to talk
about today
yeah
so
um I want to start with a little quote
and it's rumination is the coin of my
realm interiority breeds interiority and
we will see that this might be literary
true and this is why I think it's a good
quote to start with so what is
rumination
it is
uh defined by the APA as obsessional
thinking involving excessive repetitive
thoughts or themes that interfere with
other forms of mental activity
it is a common feature of OCD and
generalized anxiety disorder I actually
don't know why these two disorders were
chosen first but well here we go I just
quoted them here I would add a major
depression to the list and at least in
my mind measure depression is the
Prototype
disorder for rumination but sure OCD and
generalized anxiety disorder also has a
lot of rumination going on
and here you can see a first really
important Point namely that rumination
is its runs diagnostic marker right it's
important for multiple uh psychiatric
conditions
and yeah as said it's it's an important
Trends diagnostic risk factor and it can
predict actually depression scores and
subsequent measurement time points and
this is what makes it interesting there
was like a Grant and small Grant
proposal by I believe the welcome trust
in in the UK where they gave grants for
writing systematic reviews about Trends
diagnostic topics in mental health and
unsurprisingly
rumination is one of the topics where
they gave or where they wanted to have
systematic reviews for which
yeah they can see that it's an important
topic where people really believe that
it has some
um has some utility clinical utility
and unfortunately it is also the case
that it's associated with worse
treatment response for
Psychotherapy and also for medication
treatment
yeah and let's make it more complicated
shall we
um the
rumination is sometimes used
interchangeably with the concept of
repetitive negative thinking and
sometimes repetitive negative thinking
means rumination and worrying
um but we will use the definition of
rumination in its broader sense today so
when I talk about rumination I also mean
worrying some of the time I just wanted
to make this clear at the beginning so I
use it in the older broader sense so to
say
yes so why would we need a new uh
concept for rumination well
reinforcement learning I would say reinf
struggles to explain the constant
continuation of ruminative thinking to
make it short why should you continue
with doing something that is not giving
you like pleasure or any good feelings
in the short or the long run
and yeah why is something continued
despite not promoting
um action and also leading to depressed
mood this is a question at hand it's not
an easy question to answer I would say
and this is why we would say that we
have to not only take exploitation
learning into account but also take
exploration learning or surprise
reducing learning or free energy
minimization into account however you
want to call it the important part is
um you have to take into account that
not all learning is done to
um
uh in the sense of like reinforcement
learning but there's also learning that
we do to know more about the world and
if this goes wrong rumination can occur
and this is how we want to rephrase it
today
yeah so this is a roadmap for today we
want to reconceptualize rumination as an
extreme case of failed mental problem
solving we want to present a model of
rumination using active inference
terminology so this will be a conceptual
model we don't have the mathematics to
back it up at the moment I will talk
about this limitation at the end again
and we will also discuss neurobiological
correlates shortly
to then continue to point towards
treatment implications of the model
so the next part is like I want to talk
a little bit about problem solving and
mental problem solving and I've had a
classic quote by Richard Dawkins that I
really find interesting in this context
it says survival machines that can
simulate the future are one step ahead
of survival machines who can only learn
on the basis of over trial and error the
trouble with over trial is that it takes
time and energy the trouble with overt
error is that it's often fatal
stimulation is both safer and faster
yeah and I think this is really
interesting and we
um
can talk about also like this
evolutionary perspective later
I have really broken down into simple
terms first okay so when I want to solve
problems uh using my mind what do I need
to do well at first I need to think
about what to do next what do I want to
think about so to say the
um and we have called this step
candidate sampling so it's meter policy
basically so what do I even want to
think about before thinking about what
are important tasks of today for example
and then the next step is policy
evaluation or if I think about that what
are the expected results if I tell them
about this concept will they understand
my talk today for example and then let's
say yes I hope this that this is the
case then we have to do another step
um and do like the actual problem
solving okay now I'm convinced that this
might be the right way but how to do it
how to actually solve the problems which
are the steps necessary and
these three steps we will consider over
and over again today
and we have in the paper a neat little
example that happens to me a lot that's
um one of the reasons I really chose
today imagine you lost your key
and now
um what we typically do is at first we
check the usual places or have her put
it there no have a maybe put it there no
and after a while if this doesn't work
my policy changes typically and I think
okay
um where did I see my key the last time
that I saw it and trace it back and
maybe this works and I find my key back
and a few days after I have the same
problem again because I already lost my
key again and what I may do after a few
instances of this behavior is like okay
I need to change something fundamentally
in order to get my key back faster and
so in Bayesian learning terms at the
beginning uh my expected prediction
error minimization is just
search the usual places it might work
okay after a while uh
the mental policy okay why do I keep
losing the key and how do I solve this
problem might lead to a higher expected
free energy minimization or prediction
error reducing properties and this is
why I switched the policy right after a
while so this meter policy step decides
how to go or how to go about a given
problem in this case how to find my key
good
this is really important we cannot
search the interactively large
probability distribution for this step
it's not possible to remember all
instances where I lost my key and to
compare like promising strategies based
on the whole distribution I'm not able
to do this and
so uh it's no machine no living being we
have to find fitting samples so to say
and fitting means
um it's usually based on heuristics what
did I do with the last time when the key
was gone how can I find it this will
become important later because these
heuristics can run into problems they
help us
um like make computationally intractable
problems uh solvable but these
heuristics have also their downsides as
we're going to discuss
okay
then step two now uh policies are then
selected if they provide a trade-off
between pragmatic and epistemic value
and pragmatic is okay they I have a good
chance of finding my key back to stay on
the example in epistemic is I learn also
something about finding keys or
understand the world better
and uh
this is also important whenever I choose
a specific policy
um High opportunity costs may arise what
I mean with that is like when I pursue
like a searching process for example for
finding my key I cannot continue
preparing my talk or something like that
so every decision I make and um has
necessary costs because I cannot pursue
other goals in the same time and this is
also becoming uh going to become
important
so in order to be chosen by an organism
each a chosen policy has to outweigh the
resulting opportunity costs uh otherwise
it's not adaptive
right
okay and now the last step
um the mental problem solving good I now
decided for one strategy of finding my
key
and now I have to actually pull it off
so where to search what to do next which
sequences of movements do I have to
perform
uh and how to go about it best and
um typically in different strands of
literature not just in active inference
I need to perform something that is
called it research you know this from
chess playing typically or for class
computers like they do it a lot better
than we do but they look okay if I do
this move
um and he does this move then I can do
this move and in all move that follow it
I have a good position and it's again
not possible to search the whole tree
because the more branches it becomes
um the more branches are data branches
of these branches again so uh the tree
growth exponentially so I need to have a
strategy of not searching through all
the branches it's called the pruning
strategy in the case of Bayesian
learning it's often Occam's window
meaning that branches are not searched
through if they don't promise a
prediction error minimization that is
sufficient to pursue searching them
this can also lead into problems because
it's a branch at first doesn't provide
enough
um prediction error and minimization it
will not be searched through
despite the fact that it could have some
prediction error minimization further
down the road so to say
but we have to prune again because it's
not possible to search the whole
distribution
okay
so with these three steps in mind we can
have the following model so we have the
candidate sampling uh how to go about
the lost key so to say policy evaluation
if I do the strategy have I do I have a
good chance of finding the key and
learning something about the world
and mental problem how to actually pull
the strategy off and I want to say one
really important thing and this is an
increase in mental problem solving is a
normal process in a lot of situations
right so for example if I lose a person
that is really important for me it's
normal that my general models had
decreases like a lot of my strategies
for getting social supports don't work
anymore because the person's gone and so
uh in in in Bayesian terminologies
prediction errors increase after such an
event and this is a normal process
um and if like my general model if it
declines this was linked in the active
inference literature to bad mood or to
yeah feelings of sadness for example
and in such cases typically you think
more about a fundamental things in your
life everybody knows it and has
experienced it if you don't feel well
you tend to think more and to try to get
into a better situation again
and hopefully what happens then is okay
I
uh for example I lost someone my social
support system is breaking together
um or it's breaking apart it's falling
apart so after a while I searched for
people that I like and that can form a
new bond with
um and hopefully after a while my
prediction errors become smaller again
but therefore I need to take action I
need to think about what to do with my
life
um how to get to know new people in this
example to like reduce my
um prediction errors in this case
regarding social support and then I have
to pull it up I I have to go to certain
places to meet people and hopefully
after a while of sadness and difficult
times
um my general model fit increases again
but this is not always the case as we
know uh want to discuss next so I have
yet another quote you will get to you
get to use to quotes today sorry uh the
next quote is about rumination and it
says uh shut up she tells her monkey
mind please shut up you pick off nips
press of bruises counter of losses
Sierra or failures collector of
grievances future and past
and now we want to discuss what happens
when this doesn't work so
it can happen that despite trying agents
and organisms don't find good
approximations for important problems in
their life right and if this is the case
the prediction errors regarding these
problems stay high because the surprisal
doesn't get resolved and
um despite trying the organism tries
over and over again prediction errors
say hi surprisal doesn't get uh resolved
and the prediction error doesn't reduce
again and the problem stays and what we
now want to do is discuss reasons for
why this happens in depressive
rumination
and at first we have to say Okay a
typical rumination problems have a high
complexity with uncertainties at many
hierarchical levels if you think about
problems for example like
why is the world such a cruel place for
example this could be a nice rumination
problem
um
you would have to gather a lot of
evidence from different strains it's
really hard to actually disprove such a
claim or to prove such a claim or even
to say what it means
and this is why there might be no
efficient solution for such a question
it's not like navigating a maze or
something like that but it's much more
complicated
and
in addition sometimes like we human
beings have a very high Precision
demands for solutions for example after
I may have survived a traumatic event I
might be really reluctant to go to
similar looking places again and I have
to be really really sure that the new
place
uh where I don't want to go is really
different from the place where something
bad happened to me and if I'm not sure
and sure means really through a high
Precision I won't go there
and
these complexity demands can also make
an efficient approximation to a problem
improbable
and
this might be one reason why problem
solving isn't functioning in the case of
depressive rumination
another reason might be uh over pruning
and missing action policies so as I said
beforehand like pruning in order to
uh function properly
um
or let's say this way pruning is a good
strategy when
the
parts of the search tree that I removed
so to say don't yield like at the
beginning small losses and at the end
large gains because if it's like that
the three branch might be pruned away
despite actually helping the organism to
reduce surprisal but the organism will
never find out because it gets put away
and
the next thing is also action policies
can all only be thought through if an
agent knows about them we know about a
lot of depression patients with a lot of
childhood adversities that actually
don't know a lot of strategies for
navigating social environments
um it's not their fault it's the
consequence of childhood adversities but
nevertheless this is a problem if I
don't know the solution for a social
problem I cannot approximate a solution
because action policies are missing
and
the next problem might be that after
many failed attempts of problem solving
um
I might not even have a reason to engage
in deeper instrumental learning what I
mean with that I go back one slide
um after a while I have an idea so okay
why is my life becoming so shitty uh it
is because I don't
engage with other people anymore I just
lie in my bed and feel sad okay
and now normally there would be a step
where I think about how to engage with
other people again but if I have for
example missing action policies really
bad mood and not a lot of strategies I
might think this through shortly and
think well I can try but they won't like
me anyway
so instead of deep mental problem
solving I uh jump back to step one which
is why uh do I have so many problems
with other people and there you can see
your ruminated circle is forming in no
deeper engagement is possible anymore
and if this happens my prediction errors
stay large and
more candidate sampling occurs okay
I cannot solve this by meeting other
people but maybe I can do it on my own
no I feel so sad and lonely you see
where this is going I do not engage
anymore in deeper problem solving but
instead thinking through a lot of policy
candidates and none of them is like
giving me confidence that I can solve my
problems so I
um stay at the same meter policy
selection step so to say
and in consequence I have less
instrumental thinking and less
instrumental learning
and this also has consequences
um for example the pragmatic value of
policies are estimated to be low due to
low model fit and this even becomes
worse over time so if I think I cannot
do it I will not train it if I do not
train it
I become even worse at doing it and so I
want
I will
it becomes more and more improbable that
I try because my action policies become
more and more undertrained
and
yeah this is another really important
problem
and the next problem is the opportunity
costs because illuminate a lot so now we
are at a meter level I don't do much
else and because I don't do much else my
models it further declines and yeah the
rest we talked about on the last slide
so
um ruminative States may be learned as
agents default response for
quote-unquote dealing with problems
after a while and now we have a vicious
cycle here
and
the next uh thing that I want to discuss
is
um how neurobiology might play a role
yeah and I have had a little joke of
Phil Colette ripped off for my slides
here
um and uh quotation by Carl Friesen that
says an agent does not have a model of
its word it is a model in other words
the form structure and states of our
embodied brains do not contain a model
of the sensoriums they are that model
and on the right you can see like uh
Yale School of Management guy that
actually really embodies this Principle
as he's clearly showing on his backpack
yeah
okay Jokes Aside
um
what is first to be said uh the default
mode network is going to be important
for our discussion here the default mode
network is a large scale network with
media frontal temporal and parietal
region from the brain it's important for
introspection self-referential thinking
and autobiographical recoil so in short
it's important for everything mental
problem solving and rumination related
or a lot of these things and this is why
it's unsurprisingly going to play a role
here
and
um to be more precise the frontal
courtesies seem to be the main driver of
a memory recall in the default mode
Network so if the default mode Network
tries now I'm intramorphophizing it
um to recall a memory so
where do I find the key for example it
uses the frontal regions to be the main
driver of this process
and
it is the case that meter studies found
a stronger coupling and the hyper
activation in default mode Network
structures to be correlated with with
ruminations and they're actually two
meter analysis that found this
and it is also suggested that a coupling
with a subgranule cortex might
contribute to the negatively valence
Nature's rumination MDD
so we know okay
dmn is important for problem solving and
for rumination and it's also found
meta-analytically that it indeed plays a
role for a rumination or at least it's
correlated
and
in addition meta studies also found
evidence for a reduced frontal parietal
control Network within network
connectivity in major depression
and this is also interesting because as
we discussed our idea is basically that
rumination means I get stuck in abstract
thinking and don't use my instrumental
learning capabilities as much and so it
makes sense that in MDD we find reduced
control Network or frontal parietal
control network activity
note by the way that this part of the
evidence line is more indirect than the
part before right I don't want to gloss
over this so
while we have here a direct correlation
with rumination in the case of the
default mode Network here it's more MDD
in general this is why we also wrote it
much more careful in the paper because
it's a more indirect line
and I don't want to gloss over that
and
it is further more known that the
connection between control networks and
default mode networks is seem to be
reduced and interestingly these two
networks have to
connect in order to solve complicated
problems they actually study about that
and these studies suggest that if the
problem gets harder for an individual it
uses more of the default mode Network to
do the meter thinking and then the
control networks to do the problem
solving and the interplay between the
two is really important and okay so in
conclusion
and what we think could be the case is
that the default network is hyperactive
and Hyper connected because it does the
policy candidate over sampling that we
talked about before and
the reduced mental problem solving or
instrumental learning
um due to the policy oversampling is
reflected by the reduced resting state
activation in the hypo connectivity of
the control networks and also of
integration hubs like the insula
okay
then a short citation it will be the
last one and it's the existentialist
model and it says simply existence
precedes essence and it wants us to say
okay
um in the first instance we are being
that get thrown into the world but we
have to do something with our lives in
order to flourish and give it give
ourselves
reasons to live and to succeed and I
want to talk about a little bit about
like how can we get out of ruminative
loops and what might be old idea and new
ideas at first I want to say there's
good evidence for the effectiveness of
excrete of existing psychotherapeutical
treatment regarding depression in
general
and it's also regarding rumination so we
also have like meta-analysis uh
specifically analyzing rumination
however
um we have substantial non-responder
rates for Psychotherapy and also for
current medication approaches we have a
higher chance for relapse after
depression is gone it will oftentimes
reoccur in the life of patrons
unfortunately and we also have
substantial therapy dropouts so patients
actually leaving therapy
so it's really easy to say that uh
psychological and pharmacological
treatment needs Improvement so they are
effective but they don't help everyone
and there's a lot of room for
improvement here
and there are multiple ideas that we
briefly discussed in the paper and the
first is like a simple idea but could be
quite effective and has also meter
analytical evidence that it helps and
this is like reduce memory interference
and rumination by physical exercise in
the everyday life of patients so doing
more like especially endurance exercises
actually helps reducing rumination even
when compared to active treatment like
CBT so maybe the present patients don't
only need a therapy to be paid for but
also to have a personal trainer that
might be paid for and I only say this
half jokingly this could improve the
life of a lot of people
and another idea is more medical it's
psilocybin or ketamine was was shown in
in studies to increase the sampling
entropy of the brain and this could also
be an interesting
aspect because we've learned that the
samples are getting repeated over and
over again but um if we could have a
idea for how to increase the variance of
samples drawn when a probability that
one sample is actually a good idea for
thinking through increases however I
have to say cautionary notes especially
with
um psychedelic drugs because uh
it is a promising pharmacological Avenue
probably but at the moment we have
really small sample sizes it's hard to
Blind for these drugs between groups I
mean you know when you're tripping it's
it's quite easy to know so this makes
rcts difficult
um and we know from a lot of
questionable research practices from
this line of research unfortunately I
don't want to say that everybody in
these fields are doing bad science it's
not what I want to say but I know from a
few cases where
prerequisite protocols don't fit the
results that were presented and stuff
like this and if you combine all this
it's actually quite hard to say whether
these work really well so what we would
need is really larger study
uh not the small brain Imaging studies
with 20 subjects more like 200 subjects
would be a beginning
um and we need the researchers to
actually stick to predefined
interpretations of their results so we
can learn about more about this province
promising Avenue okay
and more ideas would be uh to change
therapy a little bit and uh concrete
idea is
we could actually
[Music]
um add problem complexity estimations uh
into therapy what I mean with this is
like ask patients okay how much time you
spent ruminating
what typically are the results of these
processes
um
what are the costs of those processes so
we could try to make the costs of the
process more explicit to the patient and
to give them a grasp on how much
opportunity costs they invoke on
themselves by the process it's not
typically done at the moment but it
could be an idea for improving CBT
and
what is also important this is done in
CBT what I now tell by the way but it's
really important to keep it in mind we
learned that we a good problem solving
requires an intricate interplay between
default mode Network and brains control
networks so it's actually important to
have optimal difficulties for Behavioral
tasks given to patients if it's too
difficult they will not do it and if
it's too easy they will not learn
anything from that nor epistemic value
is mine so to say and both options are
not good for reducing rumination
and there's actually another
experimental treatment that shows some
success and it's called emotional
flanker tasks in these tasks
um
like patients learn how to shift their
attention away from Bad emotions and
this could also help like stop the
ruminative process because we learn that
depending on your mood you will have
different heuristics in your brain about
what to think about next and in the case
of bad mutes you don't have the best
heuristics so this is another idea for a
treat for better treatment
yes
now I want to talk about a few
limitations and then we can enter the
discussion so one limitation is clearly
that the model only discusses typical
depression where Behavior breaks down
however there are cases of agitated
depression where behavioral output
actually increases
or to make it more abstract depression
is a really heterogeneous subject and
also rumination is really heterogeneous
so we don't have a model actually at the
moment that considers all individual
trajectories so this is only a general
scheme so to say but it will not fit
every individual
and the next thing is we describe
plausible ways for rumination
development but we do not know whether
these Pathways play a causal role in MDD
development I said briefly that uh when
I have rumination at time Point T I will
have more depression at time Point t
plus one but we do not know whether this
is the causal Factor but or only a
coincidence in time you know what I mean
so this is also an unsolved problem at
the moment
and the last problem which is also
important for the active influence nerds
in the community is it's not a
mathematical model it's a conceptual
model that we did and so the next step
would be to make a mathematical model
out of it for example like a partially
observable Markov decision process or
something like this
um in order to be able to simulate it
um and to check whether the behavior
that we set it would come out actually
come out so this is another major
limitation of the paper
yes I will skip over that I guess
um we talked about this enough
um so what I want to talk about shortly
before entering the discussion is other
projects that we want to do next
uh with respect to actors in France and
what we actually have done and it's now
at under review at psychological
medicine is uh applying the access
inference framework to heterogeneous
social experiences and behaviors and
this is actually done in a mathematical
precise way so there we have a
hierarchical prompt uh or partially
Observer the mark of decision process
model and we use it for trying to
explain like social withdrawal or other
social problems in depression
so it's a little bit rumination adjacent
and it's more mathematicized a preprint
is available but it's not yet through
the revision process and what we also
want to do is like simulate distorted
social functioning in May Intel
disorders
um and also to compare these simulations
or computer simulations based on active
inference
um to empirical data because this is
also what we found in the literature to
be missing we have the simulation
studies right where we have like these
simple games where active inference
computer agents play uh like a trust
game or something like that or where you
simulate hallucinations and psychosis
and these are really good studies don't
get me wrong but what is missing in our
view is a little bit combining these
computer simulations with the behavior
of human being to compare them with on
within one and
um one of the same design and this is
what we aim to do
but it's an ambitious project and we are
not finished so this will take more work
and another project that we actually
will finish this year and we have done
the literature screening is we have
prepared like a systematic review of all
active inference literature that is of
interest in for psychological treatment
and this will hopefully at least be a
pre-print this year yeah so thank you
these are my co-workers and different
projects to drop a few names on the left
of Matthias Feldman then Lucas kirschner
and to be as cool with these are the
guys where that I wrote the rumination
paper with then there's Angelina cheese
from a theoretical cognitive science
groups and she does a lot of the
computer models for our new projects uh
so we need actually
scientists that are better at
programming than I am
um to and she is doing a lot of the work
here and then there's Philip Hartsock
and bergett climb and with those two
people uh I also collaborated on uh
predictive processing model of PTSD
which was also
um published in neuroscience and
biobehavioral reviews at 2020. yeah so
with that
I would like to thank you for listening
and
um yeah we can discuss a few questions
if you want now
awesome
thank you
okay
all right well thanks for the great
presentation looking forward to the
um discussion so just to sort of begin
how did predictive processing and active
become integrated with your and your
colleagues research Direction were you
looking for integrative Frameworks and
came across this area or did this
motivate you to study and enter into the
clinical space
um
it's a mixture of two things I would say
one is like observations in patients
um maybe start with that so
my friend Tobias Uber got me interested
in this stuff and he had a patient and
this patient was
um
like really uh had had to struggle with
social phobia and
what was interesting about him that he
was discarding information
that would challenge his world for you
so to say right so whenever somebody
said that he actually liked him this one
said oh no he just pretends to say this
because he wants to be a nice guy but in
reality nobody likes me and this is what
got us interesting interested in this
line of thinking about information
seeking for example how do organisms
seek information to
uh to run their lives but also how do
organisms discard information
uh and stay in a depressed or in an
anxious state
and this is I guess one of the reasons
why we started to get interested in
active inference
and another reason
[Music]
um comes from my love or love from a lot
of my colleagues
um for simple explanations and I don't
mean simple as mathematically simple
because I don't get most of the mass to
be honest fully but simple in the sense
of we can have a only a few axioms and
explain sentient Behavior with it we can
computer simulate behavior in it and it
actually produces interesting Behavior
patterns that we know from the
literature and this is the other reason
why we got into it
awesome so many directions and ways to
go but one
uh excerpt from the paper that that
jumped out at me was the line between
adaptive problem solving and
self-perpetuating maladaptive ruminating
so
how do we know that line and how does
that play out when you're in the
clinical context like what is the
appropriate amount of thinking or
overthinking
how do we really find that line and come
to know it
that's a short answer that is we don't
where the line is because I mean in
principle maybe you find a good solution
if you ruminate just two hours more
right you never know but we have an
answer in the clinical field in practice
and it's like a pragmaticist answer and
it only goes okay if you suffer a lot
and don't get your everyday life sorted
out then it becomes a problem
and we have like measures for that so
you can assess the global functioning
level of a person and say
can he continue to work healthy friends
has he or she free time activities and
actually
fulfill her or him and this way you can
at least say okay
um has this person a good good level of
functioning and if not does rumination
impair this level of functioning and uh
yeah this is a really pragmaticist
answer sorry for that but this is how we
do it in clinical practice
totally totally makes sense
um also in that kind of clinical area so
I was curious other than rumination what
other trans diagnostic risk factors what
are some examples of those risk factors
and how
might they be linked together in a kind
of holistic understanding or what what
is the active and non-active way of
thinking about the causes and
consequences of these trans diagnostic
risk factors
yeah yeah one that jumps to mind is
emotion regulation that comes up over
and over again
um so this is a risk factor also for
depression it's a risk factor for
borderline personality disorder but it's
also a risk sector for violence
so a lot of things are connected to to
poor emotion regulation
and
um
I have to think shortly to get an active
inference answer out of that
um
there's actually a paper a new one by my
colleague Philip Herzog about like a
predictive processing model of uh of
borderline personality disorder where he
describes in more detail so he is the
expert there
um but
maybe we can just look it up before I
make stuff up that's it not to can I
just search it shortly and give this as
an answer
yeah
this is a internet extended cognitive
rumination
yes because I don't feel confident
enough to talk about the stuff that was
not my main area of research
so extended rumination you you
understand it you could make a script or
a computer program that just
iterates
and whether it experiences that in an
anxious way kind of a second question
but at least from that functional
side it's it's uh as if ruminating
yes
that's the paper here
[Music]
yes thank you
yeah so
um let's see here they actually have a
model of the connective inference terms
so let's see
where it starts
and it's actually not so simple
so
um okay so what they want to explain is
basically how childhood male treatment
leads to borderline personality disorder
and this is important for my trans
diagnostic marker of reduced emotion
regulation because uh bad emotion
regulation is the symptom of borderline
personality disorder
and
um
what they
say is
okay let's see
that we have two relevant factors here a
strong negative belief about the self
and others it's also typically known for
uh Borderline Personality Disorder so we
have high Precision to use active
inference terms here or Bayesian terms
here
to my prior beliefs that other people
are bad and I am also like a loser that
cannot do anything right in his or her
life and this needs of course if the
Precision of the prior is really high
new information doesn't matter and so we
have a Persistence of uh effects of
hostility because if the others are all
bad well I can be hostile towards them
or fear and of sadness
um and in addition to that also
contributing to
the temple fluctuations because we know
that borderline is characterized by
sometimes uh
um like
I really like my therapist as a
borderline patients and after a while I
really hate him and not a lot in between
and this may come about due to like a
high uncertainty of beliefs about
consequences of action so here it's
about policies so here my standard
deviation is really broad uh and due to
that
um
like belief updating regarding policies
gets fast and this is why I show like uh
instability while at the same time also
showing persistence and I show
Persistence of my world view but
instability of my behavior and
um this is how they try to explain
borderline personality disorder in
active inference terminology but this is
only me giving it a try I only read the
paper once but this might be one way how
to characterize
um
like symptoms of emotion regulation
problems in a conceptual model using
Bayesian terminology
awesome and also in this paper and in
yours it's on the road map towards
formalization not like that's the only
end point but it's going from the
empirical evidence and the ways of
thinking and knowing in the clinician's
office
through the integrative Frameworks to
the pros and to the graphics that
connect different nodes and edges this
figure and the ones that you drew
they're not exactly a base graph so it's
not exactly ready to be entered into a
computer program but yes it's also not
far from a base graph you have variables
that could basically be variables in a
base graph and so it it moves along and
brings collaborators and so on
as uh in a kind of
methodologically plural way
there can be developments on multiple
fronts and integrate the neural Imaging
and the
predispositions and then the treatment
modalities in in a way that's not just
like following the causal chain of the
etiology but rather approaching it
almost like in a reverse problem-solving
way starting with the clinician's
awareness and View and first seeking to
integrate and improve the sense making
of the clinician even without a formal
model
yeah I would totally agree to this not
much I can say about it I think it's
totally right what you said there
um maybe one thing uh in clinical
experience at least in Psychology I
don't dare to speak of other fields um
but they are backward translation is
really important so this is what you
described right so going back from the
clinical phenomenon to like uh more
precise view for example in
um uh informal modeling and
um typically
problems got tackled the other way
around and this oftentimes doesn't work
as well as backwards translation because
typically problems got uh thought
through by like
um basic scientists that are really good
at doing this formal modeling
but don't model necessarily the right
parameters from our view at least
because they lack the clinical
experience and so both parties working
together is really important like guys
like us
um bring in the important parameters or
at least where we think they could be
important from clinical practice and the
more mathematically inclined can model
them and so there could be a fruitful
collaboration between so start with
backward translation then do forward
translation then do another loop of
backward translation and I guess this is
a fruitful way of advancing a Psychiatry
and psychology
wow
so
a related question
to what extent
either today or in the future do you
think patients would be clued in to some
of this lexicon and ontology
for example is it enough to just say hey
here's the new recommendation here's the
new exercise plan
or is it explicitly oriented around
communicating Within These ways of
talking about belief uncertainty
information and so on
I think it can be done with patients and
it should be done to a certain extent
I think it's
um not plausible to teach them all the
mass and stuff like this is will not be
possible for at least a lot of them of
course sure if you have a mathematics
professor patient but it would be easy
for him but or her
um but in most cases no not that but you
could talk about Precision you could
talk about surprisal you could talk
about uh hierarchical learning and I
guess it's important to do this you
could simplify models into like uh
vicious circles
um one could easily draw a simple
vicious circle with the help of our
elimination model and uh teach them or
the patients a few patients
um adjacent words at least to better
understand their condition and I think
this is important because psycho
education actually is proven to help
right the more you know about the
condition
um
the higher your chances of getting
better are in in a lot of cases and so I
guess yes you could could teach them at
least base rules and a few simple things
not doing a lot of math but
like drawing a few graphs and try to
teach them the basics would be a good
idea because I guess everybody is can
get what precise information is and what
uh like belief updating how it functions
in principle this is teachable to most
of us
yeah one example that from the talk you
mentioned like with the loss of an
important person in our life our social
or our emotional support
policies
are going to have to be updated if there
was some Source we went to for
information and that Source no longer
became available we would have to change
our epistemic foraging and of course
this exists in the social space and so
when life changes when our generative
model or when our generative process our
Niche changes we should expect the
unexpected we and and so it's a totally
um normal
surprising but expected surprise event
that
opens up the discussion to like there
will be beliefs that will be changing
there will be new policies or policies
that you didn't previously take maybe
now is the time to try them out and
there's going to be volatility as you're
learning the consequences of action yes
so stick with it and try something three
times before saying that it doesn't work
um even without appeal to mathematics
that's very powerful and I think the way
that uh somebody might say well in this
double-blind study these two groups
this treatment that we're going to go
with it's been shown that in this
context these two groups this group did
better and no one says well slow down
you know the t-test used a lot of
mathematics I'm not a statistics
Professor so people accept the
epistemology
of the group differential statistics and
of diagnostic statistics even though
one could do 100 phds in theoretical
statistics and in computational
statistics and so just speaks I think to
the early stage when the field is even
perceived as being math heavy because
we're in such a methodological
developmental stage
yes but there will be layers and ways of
working that will not mention any more
technical detail than someone just
saying the double-blind study has
provided evidence for x
yes
yeah I can say two things about it the
one thing is a philosophical thing
um Daniel dinette talked about
free-floating rationales right so a
free-floating rationale in case you
don't know is like when Lions go for
gazelles it's the example that he likes
to give the gazelles to these
showboating types of jumps and the Lions
typically don't go after the gazelles
that can show this Behavior but go after
the injured ones that cannot do this
anymore right
but we can be quite certain that neither
the lion nor the gazelle knows what they
are doing but it works without knowledge
and this is what he calls a
free-floating rationale there is a
rationale behind the behavior of the
lion but he doesn't need to know it in
order to take advantage of it and this
is the case for Science and this is also
the case for patients you don't need to
know
every detail of a mathematical formalism
in order to grasp some of the concepts
and
to advance you um
your understanding of the world using
these Concepts
but it of course it helps but uh for
patients it's the same and for us it's
the same and I think a free-floating
rationales are really important concept
to describe why a lot of the times you
don't need to know the exact formalisms
and another idea that I want to give is
more like a science
um
[Music]
of making Niche constructions more
applicable to the mainstream
and this is well at the beginning it's
hard because you need to program every
little bit yourself there are no
toolboxes nothing to help you and not
really books just a few experts but
after a while books come out after a
while you get toolboxes that actually
simplify a lot of the process you don't
you don't need to write the helper
functions yourself you can use the
toolbox in a lot of cases and so after a
while it becomes more widely applicable
in science and maybe at some day I don't
know SPSS or something one of the
statistics softwares maybe not SPSS has
like a way to click through active
inference algorithms let's see but then
in principle everybody can use it when
you have new problems because people
will use it without actually
understanding it but
um I would predict that it gets simpler
and simpler to to use and I would say
overall this is a good thing because
this allows a lot more scientists to
jump in on the Endeavor
thanks yeah great points
one of your quotes the short one was
existence precedes essence
and it reminded me of a 2015 paper of
friston and Mathis which is entitled I
am therefore I think and that of course
is a little bit of an inversion on I
think therefore I am which
puts rumination before the horse or the
cart before the horse or I'm not exactly
sure but I I think therefore I am
it actually puts thinking and ruminating
first whereas this existentialist quote
that you provided
Concords well with certain ways of
thinking about reflexive systems in
active inference so what did you mean
with the introduction of that quote and
how does that
existentialist angle play out in the
clinical setting
questions disguised this one I stuck
with the existentialist uh worldview and
clinical settings
um well I think it's important for
clinical science because and more so for
clinical practice because
we need to believe in a certain type of
Liberty in order to help patients if we
believe everything is predetermined by I
don't know
um
a brain chemistry even if it's true
this will make changing your behavior
hard because you can always say well I
cannot change my behavior it's all in my
I don't know genes or what type of
biological reductionism you like so I
guess we need these existentialist idea
that yours you yourself are in control
of your life in order to make therapy
work right
so we need to
at least have a compatible
uh hard English words like this even if
determinism is true we need to have uh
it's combined with some sort of of
Liberty or belief in Liberty and I guess
this is where active inference jumps in
because active inference this allows a
formal description about self-control
and then we have a definition of
um
of uh
of acting in the world and learning new
things that doesn't require like fairy
tales uh and it's compatible with
determinism
um and uh with this word for you you
have a worldview that is
um on one hand is compatible with
determinism and on the other hand allow
us for a concept like self-control
agency policy learning all the things
and so it can also be used for
psychotherapy
interesting
I hope this answers the question but
this is what I can say
yeah there's so much uh depth obviously
many threads and traditions in
in the clinical setting
and that
full stack
from the Manifest behavioral on through
the cognitive and psychological but
verging or anchored in or descended from
the metaphysical
thoughts that's a full spectrum
area that seems like it must be
navigated in the clinician's education
but even in like the one hour that
you're spending with somebody I imagine
that it could probably uh oscillate a
lot
in where you're focusing from here's how
to tie your shoe to here's why things
matter abstractly
yeah
they asked more philosophy especially
practical philosophy so therapy then one
would think because patients bring it up
all the time right I mean one of the
problems of depression if if it's going
to be really severe is this for example
nihilism kicks in and
um so nothing makes sense anymore and
then as you said why should anything
matter at all then becomes an
interesting question
and the pressing question for them
what's your go-to response why does
anything matter
oh it's a hard question
um
I would try to get
um do you always thought that nothing
matters what was different when
something mattered for you how was your
life then
um and what changed why you came to
these conclusions now and how do you
feel when you think about your old
worldview versus new worldview so I
would try to challenge their world for
you by their own worldview a few years
ago this is not always working because
you have patients that have actually
gone through a lot of difficult times in
their lives but typically like their
worldview was not always depressed
yes that seems to do multiple things by
responding to a question with a question
it puts
an active
posture back into the conversation so at
the very least policies can be selected
that aren't rumination and consequences
could be learned even if there's going
to be a a higher low Precision on that
learning at least it like opens the door
to
movements whereas just well person X
said this or that that response may land
or Inspire or not but it reifies the
pacification
and therefore may not uh
um kind of like a
inactive layer
yeah promote the movement
um yeah
yeah I just wanted to say yes awesome
everything's the same um and if you try
something like a person XY that says
this is the reason why your life works
this will in most cases not work at all
they will say something like but this
person doesn't go through that many
hardships that I did what is oftentimes
true
um or something like that right so often
it's better if the ideas are sampled
from their own generative models
from a lost part of the distribution so
to say and not from outside typically
you have to
um
to try to get them to think out of their
own world for you and not of your work
you or someone else as well if you were
this seldom functions
um so another interesting area
you mentioned the problem
difficulty complexity time uncertainty
estimations so kind of like a cognitive
task analysis in the CBT setting where
different tasks are estimated
again along these axes of how
challenging is that for you or how
complex is that task seem to you
um how does that really like play out
because it really seems like something
in the email inbox or in writing a paper
with some improved signposting
or learning even around
which tasks are hard which tasks are
clear which tasks are
um threatening our well-being
those kinds of metadata on policy
selection and being able to see that
could help us select better policy and
not to change our preferences
which is how sometimes behavioral change
is approached by changing what people
are supposed to want but by bringing
this kind of cybernetic clarity
around
action selection to support people in
different contexts making the decisions
that can then credibly be said to be
more in alignment with what they do want
yeah
yeah I mean what is typically already
been done is um to let patients guess
how
uh how they would rate the probability
of succeeding right so when we do this
behavioral therapy they are typically
asked okay
um what do you think how probable is it
that you're gonna go there until next
week
um and it's a rule of thumb by
clinicians it has no base in science but
we say if it's 80 or higher probability
one should aim for it if it's lower it's
too difficult
um but if it's trivial if it's 99.9
probability uh it's also not worth
um typically pursuing at least not
always
um but I guess a problem with that is
that I don't know a solution for this is
my subjective probability right how I
think how probable it is I don't have a
good grasp in all cases on how difficult
it really is
for me because there are all sorts of
biases that would keep me from making
such estimations I don't have a solution
for that but what would be good is to
have
um
more variables that we could uh estimate
in order to actually have more
information on how difficult the task is
but for most cases we haven't
and if when we have them we know that
What patients think how difficult it is
and how difficult it really is hasn't
the best correlation sure it's
positively correlated
but how good I think my short-term
memory for example is and how good it
really is it's not the same and this is
a hard to solve problem for clinical
science I have to think about it longer
but it would
giving patients tulo to actually improve
their probability estimates would be
great
but I guess it's also hard to do due to
all these things that you said before
right if the problem is complex
multi-layered and has a lot of areas and
good luck actually finding
um a way to estimating probabilities but
we could start for simple
problems and maybe this helps patients
but I have to think about it more to be
honest it's it's not easy to find better
Solutions there hmm
yeah even just
on paper or digitally journaling but
then eventually potentially integrating
with the kinds of formal models we've
been discussing it can be really nice to
know hey there's a lot of stuff that you
said had a below 50 chance of happening
and nine out of ten times you've done
that so maybe next time you're in the
zone of uncertainty just go for it
yeah and or just this Pat you tend to
systematically
overestimate your confidence or
um you um you over underestimate how
much other people will appreciate this
kind of consequence and maybe writing
three thank you notes a day
would be a great use of 20 minutes
um yeah these are all really good ideas
um and it's this is also
a little is like tracking certain
behaviors like uh
an easy example would be aggressive
behavior for example counting how much
like verbal aggression was shown or
physical aggression was shown over the
days
and then like uh look what the
expectation of the patient was and
comparing those two and there you could
do like basic belief updating in in a
simplified form
yeah yeah this would be a great idea
always then possible I would say when
the behavior is clear enough and easy
enough to count right as soon as if it's
getting more unclear uh this will not
work but it could work for a lot of
problem behaviors like self-harm
aggression
um
lying in bed like Forex in depression
something like that
so it makes me think about that contrast
that you provided between reward
oriented Frameworks and which would
struggle to describe rumination as it's
not in the short or medium or long term
necessarily oriented with rewards so the
only explanation becomes well something
is off in the reward function which is
kind of tautological and so that's a
little bit of a of a local and a
constrained explanation whereas when we
see policy selection
external overt movement in the world as
well as internal covert policy selection
like attention and and mental action
when we see those actions as being
oriented around reduction of free energy
which is bounding surprise and therefore
based upon what is likely not what is
necessarily the most rewarding
um it it opens up Dot
um View
to again say how many of this Behavior
do you expect to happen in the next week
yes in a dream world we would aim for
zero of events of this number you know
we'll aim for you to be full-time
employed by next week that sounds
awesome but will we honestly expect in
one two three four five weeks and then
we're going to actually be looking back
in
and then it's
um instead of maybe feeling like um well
you're gonna leave the port and then
you're gonna have to sail across an
ocean
it can be more like there are
checkpoints we're looking back at the
buoys that we passed we have the next
three buoys that we're looking towards
we can do smaller Corrections and there
will be volatility so there's going to
continue to be surprised we're not going
to exactly hit every Milestone per se
but
if we are on this trajectory we're going
to be moving essentially as much as we
possibly could in the right direction
and spending less time just
um hypothesizing about like a total
counterfactual world where the issue is
already resolved
yes and this is a method for um metaphor
that is also used in therapy quite often
right the one of the mountain climb bar
and the mountain climber typically needs
a guide if he's a newbie and what
Psychotherapy can do is like provide
like a few a good way over the mountain
so to say provide a good place for
um for resting doing the next step doing
the next step doing the next step and
yeah this is really resonating with what
you said namely we have to
take a big problem and cut it into
little problems that we can solve one
after another so
um it becomes plausible to actually
solve it yes I would totally agree
yeah who an emotional flanker tasks not
exactly sure what those would be but it
just made me think of our policy
selection throughout the day
and all of the
fires we have to put out or all of the
bubbling soups that we have to tend to
with thirst and rest and breathing and
physical exercise and all of these
different aspects to our
our cognitive and emotional well-being
it's like there's many
things to attend to which is yes why our
attention is so
a variable
as a feature it's not a bug so the fact
that we have exactly pathological or not
just neurodiverse states that involve a
fixation of attention and also the
inability to fixate attention
it just starts with
our experience of the day and of our
attention to our body and our
surroundings and to the bigger questions
that we know impinge on us but also we
can't necessarily
um have the geopolitics and the climate
change
solved just by thinking about it
but we also don't want to neglect what
are important issues and then seeing
strategies and having the discussion
about strategies and tactics in that
attentional space instead of in the
reward space not to
um you know bash or anything like that
but that conversation is about well what
should we value more or less
and then why are these values uh
translating effectively or not into
Behavior
whereas the attention and surprise angle
is like being more in the game
and your local view instead of like
watching the game and just saying well I
want this to be the outcome
exactly yeah I want to say a little bit
about this attention focus and attention
spreading that you mentioned
um I almost said it in the talk but I
say it now like for example ADHD is not
necessarily like uh disorder in the
sense that it's a dysfunction right so
it can also be described as maybe better
described as a neurodivergent
um property of some human beings
um so they shift attention more easily
and this is depending on the environment
a good thing because if you stuck your
attention at one place too much
well you might not notice what is going
around in your surroundings so you have
to be able to focus away from certain
points of attention
and you want to have in a group
individuals that have really sticky
attentions so they can focus on a task
really good but you also want to have
the other ones that have like really
floating attention spans in order to
the new opportunities or see Danger
and so I think this can be really easily
explained by evolutionary theory right
so we have uh uh variance over the
population and this variance is not a
bug it's a feature and on the more
extreme ends of the variance you find uh
phenotypes that are problematic from
time to time but depending on the
surroundings always depending on the
surroundings right so on the one hand
you might have something like ocd-like
behavior and on the other hand something
like more ADHD like behavior and it can
even jump between the two interestingly
um
but this is not necessarily
always bad it really depends on your
environment and that humans differ with
respect to this parameters is also not a
back but a feature of evolution I would
say and also a feature of our learning
history of course
totally agreed for individual and
Collective behavioral strategies
they're often discussed as if they were
context Independence when there are
ant colony foraging strategies that work
in the desert and they work not as well
in the jungle so just like it is with
our attention there's attentional
surroundings that support this kind of
work but not that kind of work or
well-being so
um
being able to talk about the generative
model and the generative process
and their engagement
in a rich
way
I guess that's what brings us together
but it's also what feels like a powerful
place to
re-gather and remember a lot of the
importance
qualitative threads and empirical
threads in this important clinical area
and also move forward in a way that's
not just adding like another
measurement onto the pile
because a lot of these models as you
continue to develop their formality and
ability to integrate data they will
provide a new view on previous findings
and patterns that may have been taken in
the t-test reward learning world to be
conclusive for this or that
will be shown to be just two darts
thrown into a huge neurodiversity space
and there might be other studies or sets
of studies where what was treated as
being all over the place
are now like perfectly in line until a
really coherent story about
for example how strong negative beliefs
about the self and others or high
uncertainty of beliefs about the
consequences of action
end up helping us
just
do what we do
yes yeah totally agree it's maybe it's
interesting there's even reconceptual
elevation going on like uh thinking
about Psychopathology and more like
evolutionary terms like uh Stefan
Hoffman for example and Stephen Hayes
Stephen Hayes is known as the founding
father of
um acts so acceptance and commitment
based therapy and those two guys have a
new therapy idea where we describe
um Psychopathology on a pragmaticist
basis so we Define psychopathology as
behavior that doesn't fit anymore the
current circumstances so there you have
the context in right and I think it's
clever to do it more that way because
for example PTSD like Behavior well if
you're a soldier in a in a really bad
region of the world this is not
Psychopathology this is
allowing you to survive the problem is
of pthd that the war comes home with you
or
traumatic event comes home with you and
now your behavior doesn't fit the
environment anymore right and I think
this is a neat way of describing a lot
of Psychopathology
as maladaptive behavior in The
evolutionary sense and typically it was
adaptive in the past
um like also what this like borderline
personality disorder slide that I have
on the screen right now it's the same
because it was adaptive in the past to
behave like this
um
in in some circumstances in a bare
childhood so to say but it's not anymore
but it's continued despite being
ineffective and I guess this is a good
definition for a lot of Psychopathology
not for all I I would say for example
there is really Psychopathology where
you have broken inference or to say and
not just
um
if for example in in psychosis in some
cases I would say yes uh you have more
like brain pathology you have more
really broken inference in the rules of
active inference don't work anymore so
to say but I don't think that the rules
of active inference don't work in
rumination they work perfectly fine but
um the organism has placed himself in
uh in a situation where they don't learn
anything new by applying the same rules
that everybody else applies so it's
broken models not broken inference and I
guess this is true for a lot of
psychopathology
yeah
um so what are your next
moves with uh
this line of research you mentioned some
of the papers what would you like those
papers to show or who would you like
them to speak to and show what
um maybe I stuck with the literature uh
review that we are planning I would like
to get to know what uh the the
literature so to say says about active
inference informed treatments this is
what I would like to find out I don't
have a lot of hypotheses I want to
screen the literature and
find out whether we can synthesize them
into an active inference informed model
of what is psychotherapy doing
and I would like to speak this model to
a clinical audience in the first place
again so I want
uh the clinical population to learn more
about active inference I know that
psychiatrists sometimes know
about active inference literature but
psychologists
at least not clinical psychologists
typically don't know a lot about it and
I would like to change this a little bit
at least
and afterwards
um the next logical step would be to
implement some of the inside
intellectual therapy programs but this
is something for more of the future but
it would be interesting whether you can
really have something like an active
inference informed therapy but now we're
talking more like five to ten years
awesome
do you have any final thoughts or
questions and then I will close with a
short quote to fire back
yes sir
no I don't have any final remarks or
questions I would like to thank you for
giving me the opportunity to speak and
now I want to resolve my uncertainty
regarding the quote
great the quote is from Henry David
Thoreau and it's drawing a connection
between the paths that we ruminate on
that we walk upon and travel upon and
then the paths in the mind so I thought
it was Africa so throw row
I had not lived there a week before my
feet wore a path from my door to the
pond side and though it is five or six
years since I tried it it is still quite
distinct it is true I fear that others
may have fallen into it and so helped to
keep it open the surface of the Earth is
soft and impressible by the feet of men
and so with the paths which the Mind
travels how worn and Dusty then must be
the highways of the world how deep the
ruts of tradition and conformity
thank you
awesome thank you for having me
till next time thanks a lot
see you bye